<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sir Beniamin Rudierd his speech in behalfe of the clergie and of parishes miserably destitute of instruction, through want of maintenance. Confirmed by the testimonies of Bishop Iewel, Master Perkins, and Sir Henry Spelman.</title>
            <author>Rudyerd, Benjamin, Sir, 1572-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116129</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1218:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sir Beniamin Rudierd his speech in behalfe of the clergie and of parishes miserably destitute of instruction, through want of maintenance. Confirmed by the testimonies of Bishop Iewel, Master Perkins, and Sir Henry Spelman.</title>
                  <author>Rudyerd, Benjamin, Sir, 1572-1658.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. Proceedings. 1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Lichfield], 1628. And are to be sold by Ph. Stephens and Ch. Meredith at the Golden Lyon in Pauls Church-yard [, London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Given in the House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: pi¹ A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with added title page possibly printed in London (STC), of: "Sir Benjamin Ruddierd's speach in behalfe of the cleargy", [Oxford : printed by John Lichfield, 1628].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16617:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIR <hi>BENIAMIN RVDIERD</hi> HIS SPEECH IN BEHALFE OF THE CLERGIE, AND OF <hi>Pariſhes</hi> miſerably deſtitute of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, through want of <hi>Maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONFIRMED BY THE Teſtimonies of Biſhop IEWEL, Maſter PERKINS, and Sir HENRY SPELMAN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEVTER. 33.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſe O Lord <hi>Leuies</hi> ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands; Smite thorough the Loynes of them that ryſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they ryſe not againe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1628. And are to the ſold by <hi>Ph. Stephens</hi> and <hi>Ch. Meredith</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lyon</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16617:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16617:2"/>
            <head>SIR BENIAMIN RVDDIERD<hi>'S ſpeach in behalfe of</hi> the Cleargy.</head>
            <p>Mr <hi>Pimne.</hi> I did not thinke to haue ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to this bill, becauſe I was willing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that the forwardnes of this Committe would haue prevented me, but now I do hold my ſelfe bound to ſpeake, and to ſpeake in earneſt.</p>
            <p>In the firſt yeare of the King, and the ſecond conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I firſt moued for the encreaſe and enlargement of poore Miniſters Liuings; I ſhewed how neceſſary it was to be done, how ſhamefull it was, that it had beene ſo long neglected. This was alſo commended to the Houſe by his Ma<hi rend="sup">tv</hi>. There were then, as now, many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations on foote againſt ſcandalous Miniſters. I was bold to tell the Houſe, that there were ſcandalous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings too which were much the cauſe of the other: Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of fiue Markes, of fiue pounds a yeare, that men of worth and of parts would not be mufled vpto ſuch pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances. And that there were ſome places in <hi>England,</hi> which were ſcarce in Chriſtendome, where God was litle better knowne then amongſt <hi>Indians.</hi> I exampled it in the vtmoſt skirts of the <hi>North,</hi> where the prayers of the common people, are more like ſpels and charmes then deuotions; the ſame blindneſſe and ignorance is in divers parts of <hi>Wales,</hi> which many of that Countrey doe both know and lament.</p>
            <p>I declared alſo, that to plant good Miniſters in good Livings, was the ſtrongeſt and ſureſt meanes to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh true religion, that it would prevaile more againſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16617:3"/>papiſtry then the making of new lawes, or executing of old. That it would counterworke courte-conſcience and luckewarme accommodation. That though the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Miniſters bee neuer ſo glorious within, yet out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward poverty will bring contempt vpon them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amongſt thoſe, vvho meaſure men by the acre, and vveigh them by the pound, vvhich indeed is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of men.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Pimne,</hi> I cannot, but teſtifie how being in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> I vvas exceedingly ſcandalized to ſee the poore ſtipendiary Miniſters of the reformed Churches there deſpiſed &amp; neglected by reaſon of their poverty, being otherwiſe very graue and learned men. I am afraid that this is a part of the burthen of <hi>Germany,</hi> which ought to be a warning to vs.</p>
            <p>I haue heard many obiections and difficulties even to impoſſibilities againſt this bill: to him that is vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, there is ever a beare or a lion in the way. Firſt let vs make our ſelues willing, then will the way bee eaſie and ſafe enough.</p>
            <p>I haue obſerved, that vvee are alwayes very eager &amp; fierce againſt papiſtry, againſt ſcandalous Miniſters, and againſt things which are not much in our power; I ſhould be glad to ſee that wee did delight as well in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding as in puniſhing, and in vndertaking matters within our owne reach, as this is abſolutely vvithin our power. Our owne duties are next vs, other mens farther off: I doe not ſpeake this, that I doe miſlike the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or putting downe of that which is ill, but then let vs bee as earneſt to plant and build vp that vvhich is good in the roome of it; for vvhy ſhould vve bee deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. The beſt and the gentleſt vvay to diſpell darkenes, is, to let in the light; vvee ſay that day breakes, but no man ever heard the noyſe of it; God comes in the ſtill voyce; let vs quietly mend our. Candleſtickes, and vve cannot vvant lights.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16617:3"/>
            <p>I am afraid this backwardnes of ours, vvill giue the adverſary occaſion to ſay, that vve chuſe our religion, becauſe it is the cheaper of the two; that vvee vvould vvillingly ſerue God vvith ſomewhat that would coſt vs naught. Beleeue it M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Pimne,</hi> he that thinkes to ſaue any thing by his religion, but his ſoule, vvill bee a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible looſer in the end. Wee ſow ſparingly, thats the reaſon vvee reape ſo ſparingly, and haue no more fruite. Mee thinkes whoſoeuer hates papiſtry, ſhould by the ſame rule hate covetouſnes, for that's idolatry too. I never lik'd hot profeſſions and cold actions. Such an heate is rather the heate of diſtemper and diſeaſe, then of life and ſaving health.</p>
            <p>For ſcandalous Miniſters, there is no man ſhall bee more forward to haue them ſeverely puniſhed, than I will be: when ſalt hath loſt his ſavour, let it be caſt out vpon the vnſavory place, the dunghill. But Sir, let vs deale with them, as God hath dealt with vs. God before he made man, made the world, an handſome place for him to dwell in; ſo let vs provide them convenient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, and then puniſh them in Gods name, but till then ſcandalous liuings cannot but haue ſcandalous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. It ſhall ever bee a rule to me, that where the Church and common-wealth are both of one religion, it is comely and decent, that the outward ſplendour of the Church, ſhould hold a proportion, and participate with the proſperity of the temporall ſtate: for vvhy ſhould vve dwell in houſes of Cedars, and ſuffer God to dwell in skinnes.</p>
            <p>It was a glorious &amp; religious worke of King <hi>Iames,</hi> (I ſpeake it to his vnſpeakeable honour, and to the praiſe of that Nation, who though their Countrey bee not ſo rich as ours, yet are they richer in their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Religion) within the ſpace of one yeare he cauſed to be planted Churches through all <hi>Scotland,</hi> the <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; the <hi>Borders,</hi> worth 30<hi rend="sup">l</hi> a yeare a peece, with a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16617:4"/>houſe and ſome glebe land belonging to them; which 30<hi rend="sup">l</hi> a yeare, conſidering the cheapenes of the Countrey, and the modeſt faſhion of Miniſters liuing there, is worth double as much, as any vvhere vvithin an 100. miles of <hi>London.</hi> The printed Act and Commiſſion vvhereby it was executed, I haue here in my hand, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to me by a noble Gent. Of that nation, and a worthy member of this houſe Sir <hi>Francis Steward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, though Chriſtianity and Religion bee eſtabliſhed generally throughout this kingdome, yet vntill it bee planted more particularly, I ſhall ſcarce thinke this a Chriſtian Common-wealth. And ſeeing it hath beene moued and ſhewed in Parliament, it will lie heavy vpon Parliaments, vntill it be effected. Let vs doe ſomething for God here of our owne; and no doubt God will bleſſe our proceedings in this place the better for ever hereafter. And for mine owne part, I will neuer giue ouer ſoliciting this cauſe as long as Parliaments and I liue together.</p>
            <p>TO confirme the complaint of this worthy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Knight: there followes the teſtimony of two excellent men of God, whoſe piety and zeale may moue ſome to conſider of the matter more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, then they haue done hitherto, eſpecially if they will pleaſe to reade vvhat is vvritten more at large in their ſermons of this argument.</p>
            <p>The Reverend and learned Biſhop <hi>Iewell</hi> in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> on Pſal. 69.9. <hi>The zeale of thine houſe hath eaten me vp.</hi> ſaith thus. In <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Goſpell hath beene receiued, the maintenance of learning hath beene decayed; and the lacke of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vvill be the decay of the Goſpell. Loth I am to ſpeake, yet the caſe ſo requireth, that it is needfull to be ſpoken: I truſt I ſhall ſpeake in the hearing of them that vvill conſider it. Maintenance of learning vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16617:4"/>an able and ſufficient Miniſtry may growe and be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in all the Churches of this Realme, is to bee vviſhed for. The good eſtate of this noble Kingdome, the comfort of poſterity, the ſtay of religion, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing of the Goſpell, the removing of darkeneſſe hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon it. One asked ſometimes how it vvas, that in <hi>Athens,</hi> ſo good and great a Citty, there vvere no Phyſitians: to vvhom this anſwere vvas made, becauſe there are no revvards appointed for them that practiſe phyſicke. The ſame anſwere may bee made for our times; the cauſe vvhy the Church of God is ſo forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is the vvant of zeale in them that ſhould either for their courteſie, or for their ability be foſterers of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and encreaſe the Livings, vvhere occaſion is, and giue hope and comfort to learned men. What ſaid I? encreaſe? nay the Livings and proviſions which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore vvere given, are taken avvay.</p>
            <p>Haue patience, if any ſuch bee here (as I vvell know there are) vvhom theſe things touch. Suffer mee to ſpeake the trueth, it is Gods cauſe; the Livings of ſuch, as are in the Miniſtery, are not in their hands, to vvhom they are due. All other labourers and artificers haue their hire encreaſed double as much as it was wont to be; onely the poore man that laboureth and ſweateth in the vineyard of the Lord of hoſtes hath his hire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged and abated.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not of the Curates, but of the Parſonages &amp; Vicarages, that is of the places, vvhich are the caſtles and towers of fence for the Lords temple. They ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome paſſe now adayes from the patron, if he bee no better than a gentleman, but either for the leaſe, or for preſent money. Such merchants are broken into the Church of God, a great deale more intollerable, then vvere they, vvhom Chriſt vvhipped and chaſed out of the Temple. Thus they that ſhould bee carefull for Gods Church, that ſhould be patrons to provide
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16617:5"/>for the conſciences of the people, and to place among them a learned miniſter, vvho might be able to preach the Word vnto them, out of ſeaſon, and in ſeaſon, and to fulfill his miniſtery, ſeeke their owne, and not which is Ieſus Chriſts. They ſerue not Ieſus Chriſt, but their belly. And this is done, not in one place, or in one countrey, but throughout <hi>England.</hi> A gentleman can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keepe his houſe, vnleſſe he haue a Parſonage or two in farme for his proviſion.</p>
            <p>O mercifull God! vvhereto vvill this grow at laſt? if the miſery which this plague vvorketh vvould reach but to one age, it vvere the more tolerable: but it vvill bee a plague to the poſterity, it vvill bee the decay and deſolation of Gods Church: young men vvhich are toward and learned ſee this, they ſee, that hee vvhich feedeth the flock hath leaſt part of the milke; he which goeth a warfare, hath not halfe his vvages; therefore they are vveary and diſcouraged, they change their ſtudies, ſome become prentiſes, ſome turne to phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, ſome to law, all ſhunne and flie the miniſtery. And beſides, the hinderance that thus groweth by the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked dealing of patrons, by reaſon of the Impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the vicarages in many places, and in the propereſt market townes, are ſo ſimple that no man can liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and therefore no man vvill take them. They vvere vvont to ſay, <hi>Beneficia ſine cura; benefices without charge:</hi> but now may be ſaid, <hi>Cura ſine beneficio: charge or care without benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there be many which can ſay, ſuch as bee mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the Church ſhould teach freely, vvithout hope of recommence, or hire for their labour; our preachers are no bettet than <hi>Peter and Paul,</hi> and the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. They are no better than the holy Prophets, vvho liued poorely, poverty is a commendable ſtate, So ſay ſome in like devotion, as did <hi>Iudas. What needeth this waſte? this might haue beene ſold for much and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16617:5"/>to the poore, not that hee cared for the poore, but becauſe he was a theefe, and had the bagge, and bare that which was given.</hi> I doubt not there are many vvhich teach Chriſt for Chriſts ſake, vvhich ſay in their ſoule, the Lord is my portion; vvho ſeeke you and not yours; I doubt not there are ſuch.</p>
            <p>But for the hope of poſterity, I report mee to all you vvhich are Fathers and haue children, for vvhom you are carefull: although your ſelues haue a zeale and care for the houſe of God, yet vvill you breed them vp, keepe them at ſchoole, and at the Vniverſity, vntill 30. or 40. yeares old, to your great charges, to the end, they may liue in glorious poverty, that they may liue poorely and naked like the Prophets and Apoſtles. Our poſterities ſhall rue that ever ſuch Fathers went before them, and chronicles ſhall report this contempt of learning, among the puniſhments and murraines, and and other plagues of God, they ſhall leaue it vvritten in vvhat time, and vnder vvhoſe raigne this vvas done.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, what may be gueſſed of their meaning, who thus ruine and ſpoile the houſe of God, vvhich decay the proviſion thereof, &amp; ſo baſely eſteeme the Miniſters of his Goſpell? they cannot ſay to God, the zeale of thine houſe hath eaten me vp: howſoever in other things they doe vvell; howſoever they ſeeme to rejoyce at the proſperity of Sion, and to ſeeke the ſafety and preſervation of the Lords anointed: yet needs muſt it bee, that by theſe meanes forraine power, of which this Realme by the mercy of God, is happily deliuered, ſhall againe be brought in vpon vs. Such things ſhal be done vnto vs, as we before ſuffered in the times of popery; the truth of God ſhall bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the holy Scriptures burnt and conſumed in fire, a marveilous darkenes and calamity muſt needs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The oxe that treadeth out the corne is muſled, hee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16617:6"/>that goeth to warfare, receiueth not his vvages, the cry hereof goeth vp into the eares of the Lord of hoſtes; he vvill not abide ſo great contempt of his word and preachers, his owne name is thereby diſhonoured: our Saviour ſaith: Luc. 10. <hi>hee that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me.</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Theſſ. 4. <hi>hee that deſpiſeth theſe things, deſpiſeth not man but God;</hi> and thinke vvee, that hee will ſuffer his holy name to bee deſpiſed? nay his wrath is already kindled, he hath already begunne his judgements, and therefore many places are left deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, there is none that can warne them of their ſinne, none that can moue them to repentance, none that can preach vnto them forgiuenes through Chriſt, none that can inſtruct them in the comfort of everlaſting life.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe you liue ſtill in your ſinnes, in adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in covetousſnes, and in pride, without any feeling of conſcience, without any feare of God, thus we provoke God to anger; many walke (of whom we cannot thinke but with vveeping) they are the enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt; the name of God is blaſphemed among them. &amp;c. Theſe words happily ſeeme ſharpe and over ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, but the darkeneſſe of our hearts againſt God, and the lacke of zeale for his houſe, inforce me to them: wee are almoſt fallen into the loweſt pit; wee are left without zeale as ſenceleſſe men, &amp; as if vve had cleane forgotten our ſelues, as the Heathens which know not God: therefore vnleſſe we repent, the kingdome of God ſhall bee taken away from vs: hee will ſend vpon this land a famine of the word. Ieruſalem ſhall bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown and made an heape of ſtones, the man of Sinne, and they which haue not the loue of the trueth ſhall prevaile with many, and withdraw them from obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Prince; this noble Realme ſhall be ſubject to forraine nations; all this will the zeale of the Lord of hoſtes bring to paſſe.</p>
            <p>I could haue ſpent thi time in opening of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16617:6"/>matter, but nothing, in my judgement, is more worthy your good conſideration and ſpeedy redreſſe, &amp;c. Wherefore he concludes with a graue exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her Majeſtie, as followeth.</p>
            <p>O that Your Grace did behold the miſerable diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gods Church, or that you might forſee the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that vvill follow! It is a part of your king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſuch a part, as is the principall prop &amp; ſtay of the reſt: I will ſay to your Majeſty, as <hi>Cyrillus</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaid to the godly Emperours, <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian, Ab ea quae erga Deum eſt pietate Reipub. veſtrae ſtatus pendet,</hi> The good ſtate and vvelfare of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale hangeth vpon true godlines, you are our governour, your are the nurſe of Gods Church, Wee may open this griefe before you; God knoweth if it may bee redreſſed it is runne ſo farre: But if it may bee redreſſed, there is no other beſides your highnes, that can redreſſe it. I hope I ſpeake truely that which I ſpeake without flattery, that God hath indued your Grace with ſuch meaſure of learning and knowledge as no other Chriſtian Prince; He hath given you peace, happines, the loue and the hearts of your Subiects. Oh turne and employ theſe to the glory of God, that God may confirme in your Grace the thing which he hath begunne. To this end hath God placed Kings &amp; Princes in their State, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, that they ſerue the Lord, that they may ſee, and cauſe others to ſee to the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Church. The good Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> cared for this as much, as for his life. <hi>Conſtantine, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius,</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and other godly Princes called themſelues <hi>vaſſales,</hi> the ſubjects and bond-ſervants of God. They remembred that God furniſhed them in their houſes, and were not vnmindfull to furniſh his houſe.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had beautified Rome, with ſetting vp many faire buildings, hee ſaid. <hi>inveni lateritiam,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16617:7"/>marmoream reliqui.</hi> I found it made of bricke, but I leaue it made of marble. Your Grace, when God ſent you to your inheritance and the right of this Realme, found the Church in horrible confuſion, and in reſpect of the true worſhip of God, a Church of bricke; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith, dawbed vp with vntempered morter. Your Grace hath already redreſſed the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, now caſt your eyes towards the Miniſtery, giue courage and countenance vnto learning that Gods houſe may bee ſerued: So ſhall you leaue a Church of God, and a teſtimony that the zeale of the Lords houſe hath eaten you vp.</p>
            <p>Let vs haue care for the houſe of God, whoſoever is not after this ſort zealous, is a man of a double heart, wee may not halt betweene two opinions: <hi>If the Lord be God follow him, but if Baal be hee, then goe after him.</hi> Hee that is not with Chriſt is againſt him. Many talke of the Goſpell, and glory in their knowledge, but it is neither talke nor knowledge, which ſhall ſaue them in that day: he that feareth the Lord, and ſerveth him with a pure heart, and may truely ſay, <hi>the zeale of thine houſe hath conſumed me,</hi> hee ſhall be ſaued; if they ſhall not eſcape, which haue zeale without knowledge, what ſhall become of vs which haue knowledge without zeale.</p>
            <p>And you whoſoeuer you are, that haue decayed the Lords houſe, and abridged the proviſion and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof, and ſee the miſerable wracke of Gods Church, if there be any zeale of God in you, if you haue any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any compaſſion and mercy, if you loue God, if you deſire the continuance of the Goſpell; Oh remember you haue the patrimony due to them that ſhould attend in the Lords houſe; you take vnto your ſelues wrongfully that which was not lotted for you. <hi>Giue vnto Caeſar thoſe things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto Caeſar, and vnto God the things which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16617:7"/>vnto him,</hi> and make for the beauty and furniture of his houſe. Enrich your ſelues by lawfull meanes, and without the ſpoile and waſte of Gods Church. Let not the Miniſterie by your meanes bee deſpiſed. You en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched them heretofore in the dayes of Popery, which mocked, and blinded, and deuoured you: ſpoyle not them now, that feed, and inſtruct and comfort you.</p>
            <p>That reverend man of God M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Perkins</hi> in his ſermon of the duties and dignities of the Miniſtery giueth 3. reaſons of the rareneſſe and ſcarceneſſe of good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. The firſt is, the contempt and diſgrace of their calling by wicked and worldly men. 2. The difficulty of diſcharging the duties of their calling. The 3. reaſon is more peculiar to this age of the new Teſtament name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Want of maintenance and preferment for men that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in this calling.</hi> Men are fleſh and blood, and in that reſpect muſt be allured and wonne to embrace this vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by ſome arguments, which may perſwade fleſh &amp; blood: the world hath in all ages bin neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t herein, &amp; therefore God in his law tooke ſuch ſtrict order for the maintenance of the Levites; but eſpecially now vnder the Goſpell, this calling is vnprovided for, when it deſerues beſt of all to be rewarded: certainly it were a worthy Chriſtian policy to propound good prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to this calling, that thereby men of the worthyeſt gifts might bee wonne with it; and the want thereof is the cauſe, why ſo many young men of ſpeciall parts and greateſt hope, <hi>turne to other vocations,</hi> and eſpecially to <hi>to the Law,</hi> wherein at this day the greateſt part of the <hi>fineſt wits of our Kingdome are imployed,</hi> and why? but Becauſe they haue all the meanes to riſe; whereas the Miniſtery for the moſt part yeldeth nothing but a plaine way to beggerie: this is a great blemiſh in our Church, and ſurely <hi>I wiſh the Papiſts, thoſe children of this world, were not wiſer in their kinde in this point then the Church of God:</hi> the reformation hereof is a worke worth the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16617:8"/>labour of a Prince and people, and ſpeciall care is to bee had in it, elſe it will not be reformed: for doubtleſſe had not God himſelfe in the Old Teſtament taken ſuch ſtraight order for the livings of the Levites, they had bin put to no leſſe extremities then is the Miniſtery of this age, and this reaſon added to the other makes them perfect, and all put together make a reaſon infallible: for who will vndergoe <hi>ſo vile a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt,</hi> &amp; <hi>vndertake ſo great a charge for no reward:</hi> and where there is ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, ſo heavy a burthen, and ſo meane a reward, what Marvell if a good miniſter be one of a thouſand?</p>
            <p>Rulers &amp; Magiſtrates are hereby taught, if good Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be ſo ſcarce, to maintaine &amp; increaſe, &amp; do all good they can to the Schooles of the Prophets, to Vniverſities, Colledges and Schooles of good learning, which are the Seminaries of the Miniſtery: herein the example of <hi>Samuel</hi> is very worthy to be followed, in whoſe dayes the Schooles of the Prophets flouriſhed; &amp; eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though hee did much hurt in Iſrael, yet when hee came to the Schooles of the Prophets, his heart relented, he could do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no hurt, nay he put of his robes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied amongſt them. So ſhould Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates advance their Schooles, and ſee them both well maintained, and well ſtored; the reaſon is evident and forcible, a good miniſter is one of a thouſand, if therefore they would haue the number encreaſed, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maintaine the Seminaries. And againe if Antichriſt to vphold his kingdome (the kingdome of Satan,) be ſo carefull herein to erect Colledges and indow them with liuings to be Seminaries for his Synagogue, and vſe ſo great meanes to ſowe his tares in the hearts of young men, that ſo they may ſow them in the hearts of the people abroad, ſhall not Chriſtian Princes be as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or rather much more zealous for the encreaſing of the number of Godly Miniſters? ſhall Baal haue his 400. Prophets and God haue his <hi>Elias</hi> alone? great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16617:8"/>ſhame muſt it be to <hi>Ahab,</hi> or to any King, whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in that eſtate.</p>
            <p>Adde herevnto that paſſage of an excelling and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy knight, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Spelman,</hi> in his tract, <hi>de non teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis Eccleſiis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps Lay Approprietaries thinke they may hold Parſonages &amp; tithes by example of Colledges, Deanes and Chapters, Biſhops of the land, and of diverſe of our late kings and Princes. Before I ſpeake to this point, I take it by proteſtation that I haue no heart to make apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie for it; For I wiſh that every man might drinke the water of his own Well, eate the milke of his own flock, and liue by the fruit of his owne vineyard: I meane that every member might attract no other nutriment, but that which is proper to it ſelfe: yet are they greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that draw any juice of encouragement fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe examples, for all theſe are either the Seminaries of the Church, or the husbandmen of the Church, or the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and nurſes of the Church; all <hi>de familia Eccleſiae,</hi> and conſequently belonging to the care of the Church, and ought therefore to be ſuſtained by it. For Saint Paul ſayth. <hi>Hee that provideth not for his owne and namely for them of his houſehold, he denieth the faith; and is worſe then an infidell.</hi> 1. Tim. 5. Therefore before the ſtatute of ſuppreſſion of Abbies, thoſe that were not meerely Eccleſiaſticall perſons, yet if they were mixt, or had Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, they might by the lawes of the land participate Eccleſiaſticall livings, and tithes particularly. And this ſeemeth to take ſome ground out of the word of God. for the provinciall Levites (as I may tearme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> David ſevered from the Temple, and placed abroad in the countrey to bee rulers of the people, <hi>in matters pertaining to God and the Kings buſines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 26.30.32.</note> (That is ſpiritually and temporally) had their portion of tithes notwithſtanding, as well as the other Levites that miniſtred in the Temple.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:16617:9"/>
            <p>For a farewell; heare what Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 48. ex lib. 50. homil. tom. 10. <hi>maiores noſtri ideo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piis omnibus abundabant quia Deo decimas dabant &amp; Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari cenſum reddebant.</hi> Our Aunceſters did therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in all riches becauſe they did pay tithes vnto God, and tribute vnto Caeſar: but now they are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe either.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 28.24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Some were perſwaded with the things that were ſpoken, and ſome beleeued not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
